Guide to the James Gates Percival Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Correspondence, 1816-1856; Series IV; 1.25; (4 boxes)
  - Letters to James Gates Percival
    - 651.17. Buckingham, Joseph Tinker, undated (Box 11, Folder 245)
    - 651.18. Bucklin, George A., 1823 (Box 11, Folder 246)
    - 651.19. Bull, E. W., 1840 (Box 11, Folder 247)
    - 651.20. S. Burdett and Co., 1833 (Box 11, Folder 248)
    - 651.21. Burrall, Edward C., 1855 (Box 11, Folder 249)
    - 651.22. Burruss, John W., 1835 (Box 11, Folder 250)
    - 652.1. Calhoun, John Caldwell, 1824 (Box 11, Folder 251)
    - 652.2. Calhoun, William Barron, 1832 (Box 11, Folder 252)
    - 652.3. Came, C. G., 1846 (Box 11, Folder 253)
    - 652.4. Capen, Nahum, 1832 (Box 11, Folder 254)
    - 652.5. Carey, Henry Charles, 1826 (Box 11, Folder 255)
    - 652.6. H. C. Carey & I. Lea, 1825-1832 (Box 11, Folder 256)
    - 652.7. Carey, Lea & Carey, 1828-1829 (Box 11, Folder 257)
    - 652.8. Carey, Matthew, 1826 (Box 11, Folder 258)
    - 652.9. Carter, James Gordon, 1825 (Box 11, Folder 259)
    - 652.10. Carter, J. H., 1843 (Box 11, Folder 260)
    - 652.11. Caulkins, F. M., 1845 (Box 11, Folder 261)
    - 652.12. Clark, Lewis Gaylord, 1835-1841 (Box 11, Folder 262)
    - 652.13. Clark & Edison, undated (Box 11, Folder 263)
    - 652.15. Clarke, John J., 1834 (Box 11, Folder 264)
    - 652.16. Coit, Samuel, 1853 (Box 11, Folder 265)
    - 652.17. Colman, Samuel, 1825-1832 (Box 11, Folder 266)
    - 652.18. Cone, Francis H., 1825 (Box 11, Folder 267)
    - 652.19. Conner, James, 1827-1829 (Box 11, Folder 268)
    - 652.20. Converse, Sherman, 1823-1828 (Box 11, Folder 269)
      One 1828 letter gift of Joseph I. Lindsey, 1940.
    - 652.21. Cook & Smith, 1851 (Box 11, Folder 270)
    - 652.22. Cresson, Elliott, 1833 (Box 11, Folder 271)
    - 652.23. Cross, Jeremy L., 1823-1829 (Box 11, Folder 272)
    - 652.24. Curtis, J. G., 1855 (Box 11, Folder 273)
    - 653.1. Daniels, Edward, 1853 (Box 11, Folder 274)
    - 653.2. Dawes, Rufus, 1828 (Box 11, Folder 275)
      Negative photostat copy, gift of Thomas O. Mabbott, 1935.
    - 653.3. Delf, Thomas, 1851 (Box 11, Folder 276)
    - 653.4. Demarest, J., 1833 (Box 11, Folder 277)
    - 653.5. Charles Dickens Committee of Arrangements, Hartford, 1842 (Box 11, Folder 278)
    - 653.6. Dickson, Samuel Henry, 1832 (Box 11, Folder 279)
    - 653.7. Dow, Lucius K., 1824 (Box 11, Folder 280)
    - 653.8. Dunglison, Robley, 1843 (Box 11, Folder 281)
    - 653.9. Dwight, Benjamin Woodbridge, 1843 (Box 11, Folder 282)
    - 653.10. Dwight, H. E., 1821 (Box 11, Folder 283)
    - 654.1. Edson, Clement M., 1836 (Box 11, Folder 284)
    - 654.2. Ellsworth, William Wolcott, 1839-1842 (Box 11, Folder 285)
    - 654.3. Everett, John, 1822 (Box 11, Folder 286)
    - 655.1. Fairfield, Sumner Lincoln, 1834 (Box 11, Folder 287)
    - 655.2. Farnam, Henry, 1852 (Box 11, Folder 288)
    - 655.3. Fessenden & Co., 1833-1834 (Box 11, Folder 289)
    - 655.4. Finney, C., 1820 (Box 11, Folder 290)
    - 655.5. Follen, Charles, 1837 (Box 11, Folder 291)
    - 655.6. Fowler, Orson Squire, 1838 (Box 11, Folder 292)
    - 656.1. Gilmor, Robert, 1832 (Box 11, Folder 293)
    - 656.2. Goodrich, Samuel Griswold, 1823-1826 (Box 11, Folder 294)
      Gift of Joseph I. Lindsey, 1940; letter of December 23, 1823, purchased on the George B. Alvord Fund, 1963.
    - 656.3. Gorham, John, undated (Box 11, Folder 295)
    - 656.4. Gould, Benjamin Apthorp, undated (Box 11, Folder 296)
    - 656.5. Gray, Alexander T., 1855 (Box 11, Folder 297)
    - 656.6. Gray & Hewitt, 1820, 1823 (Box 11, Folder 298)
    - 656.7. Green, Duff, 1834 (Box 11, Folder 299)
    - 656.8. Greene, George Washington, undated (Box 11, Folder 300)
    - 656.9. Gridley, Horatio, undated (Box 11, Folder 301)
    - 656.10. A. S. D. & B. F. Griffin, 1831 (Box 11, Folder 302)
    - 656.11. Griswold, Rufus Wilmot, 1842 (Box 11, Folder 303)
    - 656.12. Guest, John W., 1855 (Box 11, Folder 304)
    - 657.1. Hayward, George, 1825-1832 (Box 12, Folder 305)
      One 1827 letter gift of Joseph I. Lindsey, 1940; letters of March 7, 1826, and August 30, 1829, purchased on the George B. Alvord Fund, 1963.
    - 657.1. Hitchcock, Edward, 1838 (Box 12, Folder 306)
    - 657.2. Hart, Seth, 1826 (Box 12, Folder 307)
    - 657.3. Herrick, Edward Claudius, 1838-1854 (Box 12, Folder 308)
    - 657.4. Hill, Frederick Stanhope, 1826 (Box 12, Folder 309)
    - 657.5. Hillhouse, James Abraham, undated (Box 12, Folder 310)
    - 657.6. Hitchcock, Ethan Allen, 1832 (Box 12, Folder 311)
    - 657.7. Hitchcock, Samuel J., 1825-1845 (Box 12, Folder 312)
    - 657.8. Hooker, Charles, 1820-1825 (Box 12, Folder 313)
    - 657.9. Howe, Hezekiah, 1828-1834 (Box 12, Folder 314)
    - 657.10. Howe, Samuel Gridley, 1834 (Box 12, Folder 315)
    - 657.11. Humphrey, Hector, 1823 (Box 12, Folder 316)
    - 657.12. Hungarian Committee of New York, undated (Box 12, Folder 317)
    - 657.13. Hunter, Edward M., 1855, 1856 (Box 12, Folder 318)
    - 657.14. Hyer, William, 1834 (Box 12, Folder 319)
    - 658. Ives, Eli, 1821 Sep 21 (Box 12, Folder 320)
      Certification of James Gates Percival as a scholar and Doctor of Medicine, Yale College.
    - 659.1. Jackson, Charles Thomas, 1851 (Box 12, Folder 321)
    - 659.2. Jenison, S. M., 1834 (Box 12, Folder 322)
    - 659.3. Jewett, Pliny Adams, 1842 (Box 12, Folder 323)
    - 659.4. Johnston, John, 1837 (Box 12, Folder 324)
    - 659.5. Joslin, Benjamin F., 1823 (Box 12, Folder 325)
    - 660.1. Kingsley, James Luce, 1828 (Box 12, Folder 326)
    - 660.2. Kinsley, F. J. C., 1824 (Box 12, Folder 327)
    - 660.3. Knapp, John, 1834 (Box 12, Folder 328)
    - 661.1. Lapham, Increase Allen, 1833 (Box 12, Folder 329)
    - 661.2. Learned, William Law, undated (Box 12, Folder 330)
    - 661.3. Lee, William, 1824 (Box 12, Folder 331)
    - 661.4. Leggett, William, 1824 (Box 12, Folder 332)
    - 661.5. Leslie, Eliza, 1834 (Box 12, Folder 333)
    - 661.6. Littell, Eliakim, 1823 (Box 12, Folder 334)
    - 661.7. Lockwood, Ralph Ingersoll, 1835 (Box 12, Folder 335)
    - 661.8. Lovell, John Epy, 1832 (Box 12, Folder 336)
    - 661.9. Lovell, Joseph, 1824 (Box 12, Folder 337)
      Letters of May 5 and 28, 1824, purchased on the George B. Alvord Fund, 1963.
    - 661.10. Lowrey, R., 1831 (Box 12, Folder 338)
    - 662.1. M. M. (of Columbia, South Carolina), 1844 (Box 12, Folder 339)
    - 662.2. McClellan, George, 1821 (Box 12, Folder 340)
    - 662.3. Mallory, D., 1836 (Box 12, Folder 341)
    - 662.4. Marsh, Capen & Lyon, 1822 (Box 12, Folder 342)
    - 662.5. Mead, E., 1826-1832 (Box 12, Folder 343)
    - 662.6. Meek, F. B., 1855 (Box 12, Folder 344)
    - 662.7. Menzies, R., 1833 (Box 12, Folder 345)
    - 662.8. Miller, John, 1827 (Box 12, Folder 346)
    - 662.9. Mitchell, Samuel Augustus, 1825, 1827 (Box 12, Folder 347)
    - 662.10. Moore, S., 1856 (Box 12, Folder 348)
    - 662.11. Morey, George, 1824 (Box 12, Folder 349)
    - 662.12. Morris, George Pope, 1827 (Box 12, Folder 350)
    - 662.13. Morse, Samuel Finley Breese, 1827 (Box 12, Folder 351)
    - 663.1. Neill, Miss, 1823 (Box 12, Folder 352)
    - 663.2. New England Magazine, 1835 (Box 12, Folder 353)
    - 663.3. Nourse, Charles J., 1824 (Box 12, Folder 354)
    - 663.4. Noyes, Benjamin, 1852 (Box 12, Folder 355)
    - 664. Olmstead, Denison, 1843 (Box 12, Folder 356)
    - 665.1. Palmer, Ray, undated (Box 12, Folder 357)
    - 665.2. Peck, H. E., 1846 (Box 12, Folder 358)
    - 665.3. Percival, Oswin H., circa 1840 (Box 12, Folder 359)
    - 665.4. Phelps, F. E., 1853-1854 (Box 12, Folder 360)
    - 665.5. Pond, Charles H., 1852 (Box 12, Folder 361)
    - 665.6. Porter, William S., 1842 (Box 12, Folder 362)
    - 665.7. Pratt, S. H., 1829 (Box 12, Folder 363)
    - 665.8. Pickering, Henry, 1825 (Box 12, Folder 364)
      Gift of Howard S. Mott, 1953.
    - 667.1. Ramsey, Alexander, 1854 (Box 12, Folder 365)
    - 667.2. Redfield, John H., 1843 (Box 12, Folder 366)
    - 667.3. Redfield, William C., 1844 (Box 12, Folder 367)
    - 667.4. Reed, Joseph, 1844? (Box 12, Folder 368)
    - 667.5. Rice, H., 1836 (Box 12, Folder 369)
    - 667.6. Richards, Thomas Addison, 1842 (Box 12, Folder 370)
    - 667.7. Ritner, M., 1848 (Box 12, Folder 371)
    - 667.8. Robinson, Edward, 1835 (Box 12, Folder 372)
    - 667.9. Robinson, Therese Albertine Louise von Jakob (Talvj), 1836 (Box 12, Folder 373)
    - 667.10. Rockwell, John A., 1835 (Box 12, Folder 374)
    - 667.11. Rountree, John H., 1834 (Box 12, Folder 375)
    - 667.12. Russ, John Denison, 1833 (Box 12, Folder 376)
    - 668.1. Silliman, Benjamin, 1819-1845 (Box 12, Folder 377)
      Existence and Location of Copies
      One 1824 letter gift of Joseph I. Lindsey, 1940.
    - 668.2. Seifert, Heinrich, 1854-1855 (Box 12, Folder 378)
    - 668.3. Skinner, A. N., 1832-1841 (Box 12, Folder 379)
    - 668.4. Snowden, William W., 1834 (Box 12, Folder 380)
    - 668.5. Squier, Ephraim George, 1842 (Box 12, Folder 381)
    - 668.6. Stedman, John W., 1842 (Box 12, Folder 382)
    - 668.7. Stevenson, W., 1834 (Box 12, Folder 383)
    - 668.8. Stone, S. M., 1854-1856 (Box 12, Folder 384)
    - 668.9. Stone, William Leete, 1832 (Box 12, Folder 385)
    - 668.10. Strong, Oliver S., 1841 (Box 12, Folder 386)
    - 668.11. Swett, Samuel, 1825 (Box 12, Folder 387)
    - 669.1. Thomas, B. B., 1840 (Box 12, Folder 388)
    - 669.2. Thomas, Lucius A., 1855 (Box 12, Folder 389)
    - 669.3. Ticknor, George, 1834 (Box 12, Folder 390)
    - 669.4. Townsend, A., 1825 (Box 12, Folder 391)
    - 669.4b. Townsend, Isaac Henry, 1835 (Box 12, Folder 392)
    - 669.5. Turner, Harriet B., 1832 (Box 12, Folder 393)
    - 669.6. Tuthill, Louisa C., 1847 (Box 12, Folder 394)
    - 669.7. Twining, Alexander Catlin, undated (Box 12, Folder 395)
    - 669.8. Tomlinson, Henry A., 1835 (Box 12, Folder 396)
    - 670. Underwood, Jonas, 1821-1822 (Box 13, Folder 397)
    - 671. Van Bibber, Thomas E., 1843 (Box 13, Folder 398)
    - 672.1. Walker, Samuel, 1826-1835 (Box 13, Folder 399)
      One 1834 letter gift of Joseph I. Lindsey, 1940.
    - 672.3. Walsh, Robert, 1830 (Box 13, Folder 400)
    - 672.4. Washburn, Cadwallader Colden, 1855 (Box 13, Folder 401)
    - 672.5. Washington, John Noodle, 1843 (Box 13, Folder 402)
    - 672.6. Webster, William Greenleaf, 1843 (Box 13, Folder 403)
    - 672.7. Wheatley, Ona M., 1848 (Box 13, Folder 404)
    - 672.9. Whiting, Daniel P., 1832 (Box 13, Folder 405)
    - 672.10. Whiting, Mary, 1834 (Box 13, Folder 406)
    - 672.11. Whiting, Nathan C., 1847, 1854 (Box 13, Folder 407)
    - 672.12. Wiley, Charles, 1823 (Box 13, Folder 408)
    - 672.13. Willard, Emma Hart, 1829-1833 (Box 13, Folder 409)
    - 672.14. Woodbridge, William Channing, undated (Box 13, Folder 410)
    - 672.15. Woodbury, Levi, 1837 (Box 13, Folder 411)
    - 672.16. Woods, Leonard, 1835 (Box 13, Folder 412)
    - 672.17. Woodward, George W., 1835-1853 (Box 13, Folder 413)
    - 672.18. Woodward, Samuel Bayard, 1835 (Box 13, Folder 414)
    - 672.19. Worrall, Thomas Augustus, 1832 (Box 13, Folder 415)
    - 672.1. W., Eliza, 1823 (Box 13, Folder 416)
      Contains the manuscript poem "The Strangers," with Percival's remarks on reverse along with verses in Greek, Latin, and French.
    - 672.2. White, Henry, 1856 (Box 13, Folder 417)
      Purchased from G. E. Thompson, 1926.
    - 674.1. Yung Wing, 1854 (Box 13, Folder 418)
    - 674.2. Yvonnet, James Lawrence, 1822-1824 (Box 13, Folder 419)
  - Third-party Correspondence
    - 676. Letters of introduction written for Percival, 1821-1854 (Box 13, Folder 420)
      Contains letters from E. Averill to A. Woolsey (1821); Christopher Preston Barnum to his brother George (1841); Thomas Church Brownell to Richard Channing Moore (1825); Henry Waggaman Edwards to Luther Loomis (1840); Jeremiah Day (1821); Daniel Dunbar to Mary Ward, with rental agreement (1828); Charles Hooker to Dr. Simons (1842); J. L. Jenckes to F. E. Phelps (1854); William Leete Stone to D. S. Jones (undated); Nathaniel Sheldon Wheaton to Mr. Jarvis (1824); and Thomas Augustus Worrall to Dr. Jonas Underwood (1822).
- Printed Material, 1822-1856; Series V; 0.33; (2 boxes)
  The series contains clippings and ephemera published during Percival's lifetime.
  - Invitations and ephemera, 1825-1854, undated (Box 14, Folder 421)
  - Clippings, general, 1822-1856 (Box 14, Folder 422-425)
  - Clippings, general, undated (Box 14, Folder 426)
  - Clippings, Germanic and Slavonic (primarily New Haven Sing-Song Club), 1832-1847 (Box 14, Folder 427)
  - Clippings, general, 1823-1841 (Box 15 (Oversize), Folder 428-429)
  - Clippings, Germanic and Slavonic (primarily New Haven Sing-Song Club), 1840-1841 (Box 15 (Oversize), Folder 430-431)
- Maps and Art, 1830-1840; Series VI; 4
  Includes 1 art storage item
  Series VI primarily contains twenty-two hand-drawn maps in ink, graphite, and crayon on paper; several of the maps were annotated on their versos by Percival's biographer J. H. Ward. The nineteen maps of Connecticut record in minute detail data on the geology of the state, and may have been created for Percival's work Report on the Geology of the State of Connecticut (1842) or his Geological Reports on the Middletown Silver-lead mines, Middletown, Connecticut (1853). Another map is labeled on its verso "Trap and Sandstone of New Jersey" and is likely related to material in Box 3, folder 94 (Report on the Trap and sandstone of New Jersey).
  The remaining two maps are of foreign lands: Scotland and northern Europe. The former was previously misidentified by the library as a map of Pennsylvania, probably due to the initials "Pa" (meaning parish) after each place name inscribed on it. The latter portrays parts of countries in northern Europe including Holland, France, Denmark, Germany, Prussia, and Austria. It may have been prepared for Percival's 1834 edition of Malte-Brun's System of Universal Geography; it was inscribed on the verso by Ward: Documents showing Percival's studies, but of no quotable or practical value J. H. W.
  Also here is a portrait painting of Percival by his brother Edwin Percival. He was born in Kensington, Connecticut, in 1793, studied art in Hartford, Connecticut, and died in greatly reduced circumstances in Troy, New York, about 1847.
  - Geology maps of Connecticut (16 maps), circa 1840 (Box 15 (Oversize), Folder 432)
  - Geology maps of Connecticut (3 maps) and New Jersey, circa 1840 (Box 16 (Broadside), Folder 433)
  - Scotland and Europe, circa 1830 (Box 16 (Broadside), Folder 433)
  - James Gates Percival, by Edwin Percival; oil on panel, circa 1830 (Box 17 (Art), Folder 434)
    Gift of the Misses Brandegee, 1927.
- Other Papers Related to Percival and his Work, 1859-1944; Series VII; 0.21; (1 box)
  Series VII is organized by the consecutive numbers assigned by library staff.
  The series holds small groups of material that document Percival's life. It includes some of J. H. Ward's correspondence and research notes, a folder of material regarding Percival collected by Herbert E. Gregory, and other manuscript and printed material written about Percival, including a memoir by Caroline Howard Gilman.
  - 550. J. H. Ward papers
    Material collected by Ward, author of The Life and Letter of James Gates Percival (1866), supplemented with later purchases by the library.
    - Correspondence, 1859-1866 (Box 18, Folder 435)
      Letters from J. S. Barnes, Lyman Draper, William Chauncey Fowler, Horatio Gridley, Sheldon Moore, Benjamin Noyes, and Louisa C. Tuthill.
    - Manuscript notes, chiefly contemporary reports, used in writing the book, circa 1865 (Box 18, Folder 436)
    - Letters from James T. Fields, and one letter from William Cullen Bryant to Fields, 1859-1861 (Box 18, Folder 437)
    - Letter from Chester Smith Percival, 1888 Oct 4 (Box 18, Folder 438)
  - 551. Biographical notes on Josiah Hurlbut and James Gates Percival, author unknown, undated (Box 18, Folder 439)
  - 552. Herbert E. Gregory papers, 1893-1904 (Box 18, Folder 440)
    Correspondence and research notes regarding Percival.
  - 553. "Recollections of J. G. Percival at Charleston, South Carolina," by Caroline Howard Gilman, undated (Box 18, Folder 441)
  - 554. Sketch of Percival the poet, from the North American Review, undated (Box 18, Folder 442)
  - 555. Miscellaneous clippings, 1944, undated (Box 18, Folder 443)